<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<lesson version="1.0">
  <metadata>
    <title>Present Perfect: Life Experiences</title>
    <level>B1</level>
    <duration>60</duration>
    <topic>Grammar: Present Perfect for experiences</topic>
    <keywords>present-perfect, life-experiences, travel, ever, never, been</keywords>
  </metadata>

  <objectives>
    <objective>Use present perfect to talk about life experiences without specific time references</objective>
    <objective>Distinguish between present perfect and past simple</objective>
    <objective>Ask and answer questions about experiences using 'Have you ever...?'</objective>
  </objectives>

  <lessonPlan>
    <stage name="Lead-in" order="1">
      <description>
Ask a somatic grounding question to connect body → mind → language. Example: "Before we begin, take a moment... Can you notice where in your body you hold memories of your favorite travel experience? Your chest? Your hands? Just notice, no need to explain yet."

Then transition: "Today we'll explore how to talk about life experiences in English - moments that have shaped who you are."
      </description>
    </stage>

    <stage name="Pre task A (Activate)" order="2">
      <description>
Elicit prior knowledge about travel and life experiences using Socratic questions. Use carousel for memory retrieval options.

Sample carousel questions:
- Card 1: "What's a place you've been to that changed your perspective?"
- Card 2: "Think of an experience you've had that you'll never forget. What made it special?"
- Card 3: "Have you ever tried something completely outside your comfort zone?"

Follow up with probing questions:
- "What made that experience meaningful?"
- "How did it change you?"
- "Would you do it again?"

Listen for their use of past tense and gently notice it (without correcting yet).
      </description>
    </stage>

    <stage name="Pre task B (Model)" order="3">
      <dialogue>
        <title>A Conversation About Travel Experiences</title>
        <context>Two friends, Layla and Hassan, are having coffee and sharing travel stories.</context>
        <speaker name="Layla">
I've been to so many countries, but Morocco was the most magical. Have you ever been there?
        </speaker>
        <speaker name="Hassan">
No, I haven't been to Morocco yet, but I've always wanted to go. What did you do there?
        </speaker>
        <speaker name="Layla">
We explored the markets in Marrakech, tried amazing food, and stayed in a traditional riad. I've never experienced anything like it! The colors, the sounds, the smells - everything was so alive.
        </speaker>
        <speaker name="Hassan">
That sounds incredible. I've traveled around Europe quite a bit, but I've never been to North Africa. Have you ever gotten lost in a new place?
        </speaker>
        <speaker name="Layla">
Oh yes! In Fes, actually. We wandered through the medina for hours. It was frustrating at first, but then we just... let go. Some of the best moments have happened when I've been completely lost.
        </speaker>
        <speaker name="Hassan">
I know that feeling. I've had similar experiences in Istanbul. Getting lost is sometimes the best way to find something unexpected.
        </speaker>
      </dialogue>

      <conceptChecks>
After presenting the dialogue, use concept check questions:
- "When did Layla go to Morocco - do we know exactly when?" (No - that's the point of present perfect!)
- "Has Hassan been to Morocco?" (No, not yet)
- "What's more important in their conversation - the specific time, or the experience itself?" (The experience)
- "Notice how they ask questions: 'Have you ever...?' - what are they asking about?" (Life experiences in general, not a specific moment)

Use notice boxes to draw attention to the structure.
      </conceptChecks>
    </stage>

    <stage name="Pre task C (Lang Focus)" order="4">
      <grammarFocus>
        <structure>Present Perfect for Experiences</structure>
        <form>have/has + past participle</form>

        <explanation>
Present the grammar using CARD layout:

**Card 1: Form**
Affirmative: I/You/We/They + have + past participle
           He/She/It + has + past participle

Examples:
- I have been to Japan.
- She has tried sushi.
- They have visited 15 countries.

**Card 2: Questions**
Have + subject + past participle?
Has + he/she/it + past participle?

Examples:
- Have you ever been abroad?
- Has he ever tried falafel?
- Have they ever seen the Northern Lights?

**Card 3: Negative**
haven't / hasn't + past participle

Examples:
- I haven't been to Egypt yet.
- She hasn't tried rock climbing.
- We haven't finished exploring Asia.

**Card 4: Time Expressions**
Use notice boxes to highlight these patterns:
- ever (in questions): "Have you ever...?"
- never (negative meaning): "I've never been..."
- yet (expected to happen): "I haven't gone yet."
- already (happened sooner than expected): "I've already visited!"
- before (at some point in the past): "Have you been here before?"

**Card 5: Present Perfect vs Past Simple**
Use a comparison card:
Present Perfect → Focus on EXPERIENCE (time not important/unknown)
- "I've been to Paris." (In my life, at some point)

Past Simple → Focus on SPECIFIC PAST TIME
- "I went to Paris last year." (Specific: last year)

Notice box: "If you mention WHEN (yesterday, last week, in 2020), use past simple. If you're talking about life experience without 'when', use present perfect."
        </explanation>

        <examples>
Provide multiple examples using learning cards:
- "I've eaten street food in Bangkok, but I've never tried insects."
- "Have you ever broken a bone?"
- "She's written three books, but she hasn't published them yet."
- "We've studied English for years, and we've already passed B1 level."
        </examples>
      </grammarFocus>
    </stage>

    <stage name="Pre task D (Pron)" order="5">
      <pronunciationFocus>
        <feature>Weak forms and contractions in present perfect</feature>

        <guidance>
Use think prompts for noticing: "Listen carefully to how native speakers say 'have' and 'has' in sentences..."

**Focus areas:**

1. **Contractions** (very common in speech):
   - I have → I've /aɪv/
   - You have → You've /juːv/
   - She has → She's /ʃiːz/
   - They have → They've /ðeɪv/

2. **Weak form of 'have'** in questions:
   - "Have you ever...?" → /həv/ (not /hæv/)
   - Sounds like "Hə-vyou-ever"

3. **Connected speech**:
   - "Have you ever been" → "Havyou-ever-been" (words flow together)
   - "I've been to" → "I've-been-tə" ('to' becomes /tə/)

Model examples with dialogue boxes, then ask the student to repeat. Use sentence stems like:
- "I've been to ___"
- "Have you ever ___?"
- "She's never ___"

Encourage natural rhythm, not word-by-word pronunciation.
        </guidance>
      </pronunciationFocus>
    </stage>

    <stage name="Task Prep" order="6">
      <taskSetup>
        <scenario>
You and a new friend are getting to know each other. You're sharing stories about your life experiences to find common ground and interesting differences.
        </scenario>

        <roles>
Assign roles:
- Student: Shares their real or imagined life experiences
- You (Nour): Will ask follow-up questions and share experiences too, modeling the language

Provide thinking time: "Take 30 seconds to think about 3-4 interesting experiences you've had (or would like to have had). They could be related to: travel, food, learning, challenges, adventures, or meeting people."
        </roles>

        <support>
Provide sentence stems carousel:
- "I've been to ___, and it was ___"
- "I've never ___, but I'd like to"
- "Have you ever ___?"
- "The most ___ thing I've ever done is ___"
- "I've tried ___ several times"

Vocabulary support carousel (words they can use):
- Experiences: unforgettable, meaningful, life-changing, challenging, rewarding
- Travel: journey, destination, explore, wander, discover
- Feelings: amazed, inspired, nervous, proud, grateful
        </support>
      </taskSetup>
    </stage>

    <stage name="Main Task" order="7">
      <activity>
        <description>
Facilitate a natural conversation about life experiences. You participate as well, modeling the structure.

Start with: "So, tell me - have you ever done something that really surprised you?"

Monitor and note errors WITHOUT interrupting. Pay attention to:
- Do they use present perfect or past simple? (Common error: "I never went" instead of "I've never been")
- Do they use correct past participles? (Common error: "I have go" instead of "I have gone")
- Do they ask questions correctly? ("You have ever...?" instead of "Have you ever...?")

Encourage extended turns with prompts like:
- "Tell me more about that..."
- "What was that like?"
- "How did you feel?"

Let the conversation flow naturally for 5-8 exchanges.
        </description>
      </activity>
    </stage>

    <stage name="Reporting" order="8">
      <reflection>
Have the student reflect on their performance using self-assessment widget:

"Let's pause for a moment. How confident do you feel about using the present perfect now?"

Then ask metacognitive questions:
- "What went well in our conversation?"
- "Was there a moment where you weren't sure which tense to use?"
- "Which structure felt most natural: statements, questions, or negatives?"
- "What's one thing you learned about yourself through this topic?"
      </reflection>
    </stage>

    <stage name="Feedback" order="9">
      <feedbackGuidance>
Provide corrections using highlights (hl-feedback, hl-grammar). Focus on 2-3 priority areas.

Use varied correction strategies:
- If they said "I never been to..." → Recast: "Ah yes, you've never been there, interesting!"
- If they consistently use past simple instead → Use a notice box with the rule
- If past participles are wrong → Use explicit correction with a grammar card

Example feedback card:
**Card: What you did well ✨**
- You asked great questions using "Have you ever...?"
- Your pronunciation of contractions was natural
- You shared experiences with good detail

**Card: Let's polish this 🔧**
[Use hl-grammar highlighting]
Instead of: "I never went to Morocco"
Try: "I've never been to Morocco"

Remember: 'never' pairs with present perfect for life experiences!

**Card: Your goal for next time 🎯**
Practice using "yet" and "already" in your responses. Try this: "I haven't been there yet, but I've already planned my trip!"

End with specific praise: "I loved how you described feeling 'alive' in the markets - that's exactly the kind of sensory detail that makes language come to life!"
      </feedbackGuidance>
    </stage>
  </lessonPlan>

  <culturalContext>
When discussing travel experiences, be mindful of diverse economic contexts. Not everyone has had opportunities to travel internationally, and that's completely okay. Frame questions inclusively: "experiences" can include trying new foods in your city, learning a skill, meeting someone new, or reading a book that changed your view. The grammar works the same way!

Encourage students to share authentically, whether their experiences are grand adventures or quiet personal moments.
  </culturalContext>

  <vocabularyBank>
    <word context="travel">journey, destination, explore, wander, discover, abroad</word>
    <word context="experiences">unforgettable, meaningful, life-changing, rewarding, challenging</word>
    <word context="emotions">amazed, inspired, nervous, grateful, proud, alive</word>
    <word context="time">yet, already, never, ever, before, recently</word>
  </vocabularyBank>

  <commonErrors>
    <error>Using past simple instead of present perfect: "I never went" → "I've never been"</error>
    <error>Wrong past participle: "I have go" → "I have gone"</error>
    <error>Question word order: "You have ever...?" → "Have you ever...?"</error>
    <error>Using present perfect with specific time: "I have been there yesterday" → "I went there yesterday"</error>
  </commonErrors>
</lesson>
