<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<lesson version="1.0">
  <metadata>
    <title>Future Forms: Plans and Predictions</title>
    <level>A2</level>
    <duration>50</duration>
    <topic>Grammar: Will, Going to, Present Continuous for future</topic>
    <keywords>future, plans, predictions, will, going-to, intentions</keywords>
  </metadata>

  <objectives>
    <objective>Use 'going to' to talk about plans and intentions</objective>
    <objective>Use 'will' for spontaneous decisions and predictions</objective>
    <objective>Understand the difference between planned and unplanned future</objective>
  </objectives>

  <lessonPlan>
    <stage name="Lead-in" order="1">
      <description>
Ask a somatic grounding question: "Close your eyes for a moment and imagine tomorrow morning. What's the first thing you see yourself doing? Notice how your body responds to thinking about the future - maybe your shoulders relax, or your breath deepens. The future starts in our imagination."

Then transition: "Today we're going to learn how to talk about the future in English - your plans, your dreams, and your predictions."
      </description>
    </stage>

    <stage name="Pre task A (Activate)" order="2">
      <description>
Elicit prior knowledge about future plans using Socratic questions. Use carousel for options:

Card 1: "What are you planning to do this weekend?"
Card 2: "What's one goal you have for this year?"
Card 3: "Where do you see yourself in five years?"

Follow up with deeper questions:
- "How did you decide on that plan?"
- "What makes you excited about it?"
- "What might change your plans?"

Listen for how they express future ideas - they might use present tense ("I go shopping tomorrow") or mixed forms. Don't correct yet, just notice.
      </description>
    </stage>

    <stage name="Pre task B (Model)" order="3">
      <dialogue>
        <title>Making Weekend Plans</title>
        <context>Two colleagues, Sara and Ahmed, are talking on Friday afternoon about their weekend plans.</context>
        <speaker name="Sara">
So, what are you going to do this weekend, Ahmed?
        </speaker>
        <speaker name="Ahmed">
I'm going to visit my parents on Saturday. We're going to have a big family dinner. What about you?
        </speaker>
        <speaker name="Sara">
I'm not sure yet. I'll probably stay home and relax. Oh wait - it's going to rain tomorrow, I just checked the weather.
        </speaker>
        <speaker name="Ahmed">
Really? Then I'll bring an umbrella. Are you going to do anything on Sunday?
        </speaker>
        <speaker name="Sara">
Yes! I'm meeting some friends for brunch. We're going to try that new café downtown. Want to join us?
        </speaker>
        <speaker name="Ahmed">
That sounds great! Sure, I'll come! What time are you meeting?
        </speaker>
        <speaker name="Sara">
We're meeting at 11. I'll send you the address later.
        </speaker>
      </dialogue>

      <conceptChecks>
After presenting the dialogue, ask:
- "What is Ahmed's plan for Saturday?" (Visit parents - he decided this before)
- "Did Sara plan to stay home?" (No, she just decided now)
- "How do they know it's going to rain?" (Weather prediction - evidence)
- "Notice Ahmed says 'I'll bring an umbrella' - when did he decide this?" (Right now, spontaneous)
- "When Sara says 'I'm meeting friends' - is this a plan or a spontaneous decision?" (A plan, already arranged)

Use notice boxes to highlight the different forms they're using.
      </conceptChecks>
    </stage>

    <stage name="Pre task C (Lang Focus)" order="4">
      <grammarFocus>
        <structure>Three ways to talk about the future</structure>

        <explanation>
Present the grammar using CARD layout:

**Card 1: GOING TO (for plans and intentions)**

Form: am/is/are + going to + base verb

Use when:
- You already decided/planned something
- You have evidence for a prediction

Examples:
- "I'm going to study tonight." (I already decided)
- "Look at those clouds - it's going to rain!" (I can see evidence)
- "They're going to move to Canada next year." (They already made this plan)

**Card 2: WILL (for spontaneous decisions and predictions)**

Form: will + base verb

Use when:
- You decide something right now (spontaneous)
- You're making a prediction without evidence
- You're offering, promising, or refusing

Examples:
Spontaneous: "I'm thirsty. I'll get some water." (deciding now)
Prediction: "I think it will be sunny tomorrow." (opinion/guess)
Offer: "Don't worry, I'll help you!" (promise)

**Card 3: PRESENT CONTINUOUS (for fixed arrangements)**

Form: am/is/are + verb-ing

Use when:
- You have a fixed arrangement with specific time/place
- Usually with time expressions

Examples:
- "I'm meeting John at 3pm." (We arranged this)
- "We're flying to Paris on Monday." (We booked tickets)
- "She's having dinner with her boss tomorrow." (Specific arrangement)

**Card 4: Comparison - Use notice box:**

"I'm going to see a movie." → I decided earlier, general plan
"I'm seeing a movie at 7pm at Cinema 5." → Fixed arrangement, specific details
"I'll see a movie." → Just decided now, spontaneous

**Card 5: Questions**

Going to: "What are you going to do?"
Will: "What will happen next?"
Present Continuous: "What are you doing tomorrow?"

**Card 6: Negatives**

Going to: "I'm not going to quit."
Will: "It won't rain."
Present Continuous: "I'm not working tomorrow."
        </explanation>

        <examples>
Provide multiple examples using learning cards with context:

- "A: The phone is ringing. B: I'll answer it!" (spontaneous offer)
- "I'm going to learn Spanish next year. I already bought the textbook." (plan with evidence)
- "We're having a team meeting on Thursday at 10am." (fixed arrangement)
- "I think robots will do more jobs in the future." (prediction, no evidence)
- "Look at the time! We're going to be late!" (prediction with evidence)
        </examples>
      </grammarFocus>
    </stage>

    <stage name="Pre task D (Pron)" order="5">
      <pronunciationFocus>
        <feature>Reduction of "going to" → "gonna" in connected speech</feature>

        <guidance>
Use think prompts: "Listen to how native speakers say 'going to' in casual conversation..."

**Focus areas:**

1. **Reduction: going to → gonna** /ˈɡɒnə/
   - "I'm going to study" → "I'm gonna study"
   - "They're going to arrive late" → "They're gonna arrive late"

   Note in dialogue box: "In informal speech, 'going to' sounds like 'gonna'. This is normal! But we still write 'going to'."

2. **Will contraction** + weak form:
   - I will → I'll /aɪl/
   - You will → You'll /juːl/
   - It will → It'll /ˈɪtl/ (very weak)

3. **Won't** /woʊnt/:
   - "Will not" → "Won't" (notice the /o/ sound, not /ɪ/)

4. **Connected speech**:
   - "I'll see you" → "I'll-see-you" (flows together)
   - "What are you going to do?" → "Whadda-ya-gonna-do?" (very casual)

Model examples, then ask student to repeat naturally:
- "I'm gonna call my mom tonight."
- "I'll text you later."
- "What're you gonna do this weekend?"
        </guidance>
      </pronunciationFocus>
    </stage>

    <stage name="Task Prep" order="6">
      <taskSetup>
        <scenario>
Imagine you and a friend are planning an exciting weekend trip together. You need to decide what you're going to do, where you'll go, and make spontaneous decisions along the way.
        </scenario>

        <roles>
Assign roles:
- Student: One friend making suggestions and plans
- You (Nour): The other friend, asking questions and also making spontaneous decisions

Provide thinking time: "Take 30 seconds to think about: What kind of trip do you want? Beach? Mountains? City? What activities sound fun?"
        </roles>

        <support>
Provide sentence stems carousel:

**For plans (going to):**
- "I'm going to ___"
- "We're going to ___ and then ___"
- "I'm not going to ___ because ___"

**For spontaneous decisions (will):**
- "I'll ___ if you ___"
- "Don't worry, I'll ___"
- "I think I'll ___"

**For arrangements (present continuous):**
- "I'm ___ at [time]"
- "We're meeting ___ at ___"

Vocabulary support carousel:
- Activities: swimming, hiking, sightseating, trying local food, taking photos, relaxing
- Places: beach, mountains, museum, market, café, hotel
- Time: this weekend, tomorrow morning, next Saturday, at 9am
        </support>
      </taskSetup>
    </stage>

    <stage name="Main Task" order="7">
      <activity>
        <description>
Facilitate a natural planning conversation. Start with:

"So, exciting! We're planning a weekend trip. Where are we going to go?"

As the conversation progresses, create opportunities for different future forms:
- Ask about pre-made plans: "What are you going to do on Saturday?"
- Create spontaneous moments: "Oh no, I forgot my camera!" → Student might say "I'll lend you mine!"
- Ask about specific arrangements: "What time are we meeting the guide?"

Monitor for these common errors WITHOUT interrupting:
- Using 'will' for plans: "I will visit my parents tomorrow" (should be 'going to' if it's a plan)
- Using 'going to' for spontaneous: "Oh! I'm going to help you!" (should be 'will')
- Wrong form: "I'm go to study" instead of "I'm going to study"

Encourage extended conversation. Let them make decisions together, change plans, predict weather, etc.
        </description>
      </activity>
    </stage>

    <stage name="Reporting" order="8">
      <reflection>
Use self-assessment widget:

"How confident do you feel about the different future forms now?"

Ask metacognitive questions:
- "Which form felt easiest: going to, will, or present continuous?"
- "Can you think of a moment where you chose one form over another? Why?"
- "What's still a bit confusing?"
- "If you were teaching a friend, which form would you explain first?"
      </reflection>
    </stage>

    <stage name="Feedback" order="9">
      <feedbackGuidance>
Focus on 2-3 priority areas using highlights.

Common feedback patterns for A2:

**If they mixed up will/going to:**
Use a comparison card with notice box:
"When you said 'I will visit my mom tomorrow' - this sounds like you're deciding now. But if you already planned it, we say 'I'm going to visit my mom.' The difference is: Did you already decide? (going to) Or are you deciding right now? (will)"

**If they had trouble with 'gonna' pronunciation:**
Use dialogue box to model natural speech, then encourage practice.

**Positive feedback example:**
✨ "You did really well with time expressions! You said 'I'm meeting you at 5pm' - perfect use of present continuous for a fixed arrangement."

**Correction example:**
Instead of: "I will go shopping tomorrow." (This sounds unplanned)
Better: "I'm going to go shopping tomorrow." (Shows it's a plan)

**Your goal for next time:**
Practice listening for these forms in movies or podcasts. When you hear "I'll" - ask yourself: Is this spontaneous? When you hear "going to" - is there a plan?

End with encouragement: "Your planning conversation felt really natural - I could imagine us actually taking that trip together!"
      </feedbackGuidance>
    </stage>
  </lessonPlan>

  <culturalContext>
Different cultures have different relationships with planning and spontaneity. Some students come from cultures where detailed planning is the norm; others are more comfortable with spontaneity. Both are valid! Use this lesson to explore how language reflects these differences.

When students share plans, honor their timeline - whether it's a weekend trip or a five-year goal.
  </culturalContext>

  <vocabularyBank>
    <word context="time">tomorrow, tonight, next week, this weekend, soon, later, in the future</word>
    <word context="plans">plan, intention, arrangement, appointment, schedule</word>
    <word context="activities">visit, meet, travel, study, work, relax, try</word>
    <word context="predictions">probably, maybe, definitely, possibly, certainly</word>
  </vocabularyBank>

  <commonErrors>
    <error>Using 'will' for definite plans: "I will visit" → "I'm going to visit"</error>
    <error>Forgetting 'to' after 'going': "I'm going study" → "I'm going to study"</error>
    <error>Wrong form of 'be': "I is going to" → "I am going to"</error>
    <error>Using 'going to' for spontaneous: "I'm going to help you!" (just decided) → "I'll help you!"</error>
  </commonErrors>
</lesson>
